Lucas Silva

General Information

Address: R. Luiz Oscar de Carvalho, 75, Florianópolis, Brazil.

Phone: +55 (48) 99150-3012. Email: pslucasps@gmail.com.

Page: https://lucas.dev.br.

Summary

My journey working with Information Technology started back in 2006. From there until 2017 my major focus was in academia and research. Despite my dense involvement with academia, I also was involved in practical software development. Currently, I work as a Senior Engineer and my mission is to lead the Android and iOS development teams and to drive the product architecture.

During my academic formation, I had teaching experience with entry level programmers and undergraduate and graduate students. Teaching was crucial for me to develop mentoring skills, which benefits me as a software lead developer. These teaching abilities make me able to efficiently help and guide my team members to solve technical issues.

I have a deeper understanding of software development and practices. I have proficiency with a wide range of languages, such as Java, Kotlin, JavaScript, Swift, Python, and PHP and I can easily learn new languages, frameworks and tools. Furthermore, I am a well-experienced backend and frontend developer, being able to work with both, Web and mobile development. Moreover, I also have a higher ground knowledge and experience with essential software practices, such as testing, continuous integration and software architecture.

Education

Ph.D. student in Computer Science - Software Engineering.

Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Thesis: Automated Refactoring of Test Code, incomplete.

Master's degree in Computer Science - Software Engineering.

Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Dissertation: Reuse of Code and Execution of Test Fixture between Test Classes, 2016.

Bachelor's degree in Computer Science.

Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Course completion assignment: Webis: a Language and an Accessible Programming Environment, 2013.

Associate degree in Computer.

Federal Institute of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Course completion assignment: Computer Solutions, 2008.

Work Experience

2021 to present

Senior Engineer at Communication Security Group (CSG).

2017 to 2021

System Analyst at Superintendency of Electronic Governance and Information and Communication Technology (SeTIC), Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2020 to 2021

Development Manager of Course Monitoring and Evaluation System (SAAS) at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2014 to 2021

Researcher at Software Engineering and Database Laboratory, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2019 to 2020

Developer of the Judicialization System at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2018

Teacher of the Software Testing Training Course at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2017

Teacher of the Software Testing Course at Vale do Itajaí University, Brazil.

2016 to 2017

Full-stack Developer at Britehouse, South Africa.

2014 to 2015

Developer at Lepidus Tecnologia, Brazil.

2014 to 2018

Developer of Course Monitoring and Evaluation System (SAAS) at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2012

Teacher of the Web Page Accessibility and Web Programming Training Course at Santa Catarina Association for Integration of the Blind, Brazil.

2011 to 2013

Scholarship Student of the Urban Bus Real-Time Information and Control System (SincroBus) Project at Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2011

Scholarship Student of the Social Integration in Visual Impaired Community Project at Educational Software Laboratory, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2010 to 2013

Developer at Education Software Laboratory, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

2007 to 2008

Intern at Computer Laboratory, Federal Institute of Santa Catarina, Brazil.

Computer Skills

- Object-oriented programming languages and design patterns.
- Software testing, Test-Driven Development and Behaviour-Driven Development.
- Agile software development practices
- Continuous Integration and Continuous Delivery.
- Backend development
- Front-end web development.
- Android development.
- iOS development.
- Design of RESTfull APIs

- Design of software architectures.
- Linux.

Publications

2021

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. *Estória: A Framework for Code and Execution Reuse between Test Classes*. Journal of Computer Science.

2021

Douglas Hiura Longo, Patrícia Vilain, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**. *Measuring Test Data Uniformity in Acceptance Tests for the FitNesse and Gherkin Notations*. Journal of Computer Science.

2020

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. LCCSS: *A Similarity Metric for Identifying Similar Test Code*. In: 14th Brazilian Symposium on Software Components, Architectures, and Reuse.

2019

Douglas Hiura Longo, Patrícia Vilain, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**. *Impacts of Data Uniformity in the Reuse of Acceptance Test Glue Code*. In: 31st International Conference on Software Engineering and Knowledge Engineering.

2018

Beatriz Wilges, Douglas Hiura Longo, Gustavo Pereira Mateus, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**, Renato Cislaghi, Silvia Modesto Nassar, Almir dos Santos Albuquerque. *Quality Evaluation Processes of Courses Presented in a Results Management Module*. In: 11th International Conference of Education, Research and Innovation

2017

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. *Reuse of Fixture Setup between Test Classes*. In: 29th International Conference on Software Engineering and Knowledge Engineering.

2016

Douglas Hiura Longo, Patrícia Vilain, **Lucas Pereira da Silva**, Ronaldo dos Santos Melo. *A Web Framework for Test Automation*. In: 18th International Conference on Information Integration and Web-based Applications and Services.

2016

Lucas Pereira da Silva and Patrícia Vilain. *Execution and Code Reuse between Test Classes*. In: 14th International Conference on Software Engineering Research, Management and Applications.

2007

Lucas Pereira da Silva, Diego Rodrigo Vaz and Lucas Voigt. *Cybernetic Crimes at Colégio Agrícola de Camboriú*. In: 2nd Interdisciplinary Scientific and Technological Initiation Exhibition.

Awards

2020

3rd best paper award of the 14th Brazilian Symposium on Software Components, Architectures, and Reuse, Brazilian Conference on Software.

2014

Student Merit Award. Best graduate student of Computer Science, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Brazil.